This section of the course will go through
the same six types of operators we covered
in the previous topic, but instead of working
on order of operations, we will cover what
these operators do in detail.
And we will create building blocks for games
to help understand these different types of
operators.
An assignment is a value attached to a variable,
usually with an equal sign.
In this 141-assignment code example, we see
a variable named score, on line 1, and it
is assigned a value of 300.
This assignment is known as a simple assignment.
A compound assignment changes the value of
a variable using an arithmetic operator.
Take a look at the code on line 3.
The score +=10 statement adds 10 to the score
and is easier to write than score = score
+ 10.
Many programming languages support the compound
assignment syntax.
One benefit of this syntax is one does not
need to type the variable twice, which presents
an extra opportunity for a typo and an error.
I will run this code and, using the print
statement on line 4, we see the current score
of 310, which makes sense, given that we started
with an assignment of 300 to the score variable
and then used a compound operator to add 10
to the score.
Let’s take a moment to test the other common
arithmetic operators on this score variable.
First, I will copy lines 3 and 4 and paste
them three times to create room for three
more assignments.
Get into the habit of reusing code snippets
as much as possible to ease your code building.
Next, I will change the operators to subtraction,
multiplication, and division and the numbers
to 20, 5, and 10, so we have some variety.
Then, I will run this code.
300 + 10 = 310.
Subtract 20, and you get 290.
Multiply by 5, and you get 1450.
Divide by 10, and you get 145.
The next operator we will look at in this
topic is the modulus, which is the remainder
of two numbers divided by each other.
I will copy the code from lines 12 and 13
to lines 15 and 16, change the operator to
the modulus operator, a percent symbol, and
change the number to 4.
When I rerun this code, the rest of the numbers
are the same, and the modulus is 1, since
145 divided by 4 has a remainder of 1.
In gaming, a modulus is often used to see
if any points are left over once points are
spent on items such as coins or whatever people
obtain in games.